Richard Dudman Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Richard Dudman Papers 1911-2014 1944-1983
MSS58248
Dudman, Richard, 1918-
22,000 items
70 containers
22 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Editor, executive, and journalist. Correspondence, notebooks, writings, and background material relating mainly to Dudman's career as a journalist with the St. Louis Post-Dispatch.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Carter, Jimmy, 1924-; Dudman, Richard, 1918-2017.
Subjects
American newspapers--Missouri--Saint Louis.; Cold War.; Conservatism--United States.; Political corruption--United States.; Revolutions.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975.; Watergate Affair, 1972-1974.; World politics--1945-1989.
Places
China--History--20th century.; Cuba--History--20th century.; Middle East--History--20th century.; Southeast Asia--History--20th century.; United States--History--20th century.; United States--Politics and government--20th century.; Vietnam--History--1945-1975.
Titles
St. Louis post-dispatch.
Occupations
Editors.; Executives.; Journalists.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Richard Dudman, editor, executive, and journalist, were deposited in the Library of Congress by Dudman, 1978-1983. Additional material was given from 1987 to 2014, and the papers were converted to a gift in 2002.
Transfers
Posters have been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division of the Library, where they are identified as part of these papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Richard Dudman are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1918, May 3 Born, Centerville, Iowa
1937 Photographer, Oroville (Calif.) Mercury-Register
1940 A.B., Stanford University, Stanford, Calif.
1942 1945 United States Naval Reserve
1946 1949 Reporter, Denver Post
1948 Married Helen Sloane
1949 1953 Reporter, St. Louis Post-Dispatch
1953 1954 Nieman Fellow, Harvard
1954 1969 Member, Washington Bureau, St. Louis Post-Dispatch
1962 Published Men of the Far Right. New York: Pyramid Books
1969 1981 Chief, Washington Bureau, St. Louis Post-Dispatch
1970 Captured and detained by the National Liberation Front of South Vietnam for forty days, Cambodia
1971 Published 40 Days with the Enemy. New York: Liveright
1974 Trustee, Washington Journalism Center
1977 1981 Member, advisory committee, Nieman Foundation for Journalism
1981 Chairman of the board and vice president, Dudman Communications Corp.
1988 Helped open southern Africa news bureau for South-North News Service, Swaziland
1993 Recipient, George Polk Career Award
1994 1996 Trained and coached newspaper reporters and editors, Knight International Media Fellowship, South Africa, with an absence in 1995
2000 2012 Senior contributing editor, Bangor Daily News
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Richard Dudman (1918- ) span the years 1911-2014 and consist of correspondence, notebooks, writings, and background material relating mainly to his career as a journalist with the St. Louis Post-Dispatch. Prominent topics include his coverage of the war in Vietnam and reporting on the Middle East, Cuba, Southeast Asia, and China during a period of cold war and revolutions. Others subjects relate to domestic politics in the 1960s and 1970s including Watergate, right-wing conservatism, and the Jimmy Carter administration. The collection is organized into six series whose contents reflect the arrangement and description of the material as it was received in installments from Dudman: General Correspondence, Notebooks, Subject File, Writings, and Addition I and Addition II.
In the spring of 1965, the studied calm that generally characterizes meetings of the Massachusetts Historical society was disturbed when a troubled federal judge, Charles Wyzanski, posed several questions about the course of current events.[1] Judge Wyzanski was bothered by the little-debated but widening war in Vietnam, and he asked Walter Lippman, a guest of the society, if all the facts were accessible to the “informed public,” which he defined as “the type that reads the New York papers and the Washington papers.” Lippmann replied that the most relevant facts were available, but not in the New York or Washington papers, and he praised a recent series by “a correspondent of the St. Louis Post-Dispatch who's an old hand out there, Richard Dudman.... I have checked those articles against our own intelligence sources privately. They are perfectly correct.... [H]e shows that the Viet Cong has won the war in the countryside of South Vietnam.” [2]
Richard Dudman had been a reporter for the Post-Dispatch since, 1949, and Walter Lippman's endorsement reflected the widespread respect that Dudman's work enjoyed among readers and reporters alike. His news articles and columns are a distillation of the major public events of the post-war era, and his papers provide important insights into the character of his career. The papers, listed in the 1978 [Manuscript Division] acquisitions report, were formally deposited by Mr. Dudman in 1979. They range from 1946 to 1978 and include correspondence, research files, clippings, and notebooks that document a newspaperman's odyssey. There are fascinating glimpses of half a dozen revolutions, Israeli operations in the 1956 Sinai campaign, the Lebanon crisis of 1958, Cuba, Laos, Cambodia, China, the two Vietnams, and other troubled spots throughout the world. Dudman's papers are also valuable for exploring a wide range of domestic political problems, and there are interesting files on right-wing politics, the Watergate scandals, and other major issues that have emerged since World War II. In 1969, after twenty years and over fifteen hundred stories with the Post-Dispatch, he became chief of the newspaper's Washington bureau, a post from which he continued to survey American politics and the world beyond until his retirement.
The collection consists of approximately sixty-three hundred items, and it has an organic character that gives it special value for researchers. There are clear relationships between the notebooks, the columns, and the correspondence that permit one to follow the story as it emerged, as it appeared, and as it provided the basis for Dudman's further reflections. On a number of matters, such as the Dixon-Yates plan, Barry Goldwater's presidential campaign, and negotiations leading to American withdrawal in Vietnam, there are memoranda from Dudman to his editors that show how his articles took shape. More frequently, fragments appear in his notebooks that help one understand events as they unfolded for him. Correspondence with readers and fellow newsmen gives other insights into Dudman's efforts to reconstruct and interpret the events of the day.
Wide-ranging personal interests and the multiple demands made on reporters in a Washington bureau have led Dudman to explore an incredible range of problems, but he is perhaps most frequently associated with his coverage of the war in Vietnam. Dudman first went to South Vietnam in 1962, and his many subsequent visits to the field combined with his assessment of his decisions in Washington to make him and the Post-Dispatch leading critics of the war. In early 1965, while he was in Vietnam preparing the series that Lippman praised, Dudman wrote his colleague Marquis Childs, that “[m]y own view is that the war is being lost, and in a hurry.” As events developed during the remainder of the decade, Dudman retained a commendable open-minded sensitivity to the complexities of the quagmire, but his earliest impression that the war was an overwhelmingly flawed enterprise continued to be the central theme of his reporting. Thus the jottings in his notebooks on Vietnam are particularly lively, and they reveal the human dimensions as well as the structural dynamics of war. Typical notes from January 1970 describe Henry Kissinger's deputy, General Al Haig, as “RA [Regular Army] all the way.... JCS insisted he sit at Henry's elbow. Sits on Henry's info flow.” A briefing on the situation in Vietnam was summed up as “The line—Enemy capability down,” with emphasis supplied by the uncharacteristic underscoring. “All quotas met” (and furiously underscored by Dudman) characterized the Phoenix program, an element in the assault on the Viet Cong infrastructure that included assassination. Dudman wrote several critical pieces about the Phoenix program, and his papers also include interesting exchanges with government officials who ran the program.
Perhaps the most unusual documents in the Dudman Papers are the notes he took during May and June 1970, when he and two other reporters covering the Cambodian incursion were captured by forces of the National Liberation Front. Dudman and his colleagues were held for forty days, and following his release he transformed these jottings, many of them on student's lined copybook paper, into one of the most dramatic series of the war. Other materials relating to the series and to the book that followed, Forty Days with the Enemy (New York: Liversight, 1971. 182 p.), are contained in the papers. Dudman's capture and release gave renewed hope to the families of many journalists who had not been so fortunate, and he began to play a larger role in the many efforts to secure the return of those still listed among the missing. One of the most poignant experiences of the war is reflected in his exchanges with Patricia Hangen, the wife of a missing television correspondent, and her spirit, persistence, and dignity give the tragedy of her husband's disappearance in Cambodia a special sadness.
It is appropriate that a collection which documents the full range of public issues also runs the gamut of private emotions, for there are lighter moments in the Dudman Papers that give some balance to the more somber situations he encountered. Among the most delightful notes in the collection are letters from his daughters in 1966, when he was midway through his third trip to Vietnam. Janet, a high school student, sought his advice about which modern language she should study. “I am seriously considering Russian but I don't know. Please answer because we have to answer soon.” His daughter Martha asked him “to write me about the situation there, and explain it so I can tell those guys I argue with. OK?” Such family letters appear throughout the collection, and they will provide students of modern journalism with a valuable angle of vision on the life of a reporter on assignment.
Following a tour of the Middle East in 1956, Dudman wrote Joseph Pulitzer, Jr., his publisher, that he “found government leaders impressed that a Middle Western American newspaper would send its own reporter there, and they were correspondingly helpful.” Dudman's career and the traditions of the St. Louis Post-Dispatch confirm the important national contributions that regional newspapers have made to the American experience. The Library of Congress is fortunate to have the papers of many who have been associated with the Post-Dispatch, such as Joseph Pulitzer, Joseph Pulitzer, Jr., Irving Brant, Bill Mauldin, and Wallace Deuel. Thus future students will be able to consult the Dudman Papers within a particularly rich documentary context.
Material from Addition I are mostly topical files and supplement the Subject File and Writings series. Also included are drafts and supporting material for Dudman's Men of the Far Right and Forty Days with the Enemy. Addition II primarily relates to Dudman's life and continued work in journalism following his retirement from the St. Louis Post-Dispatch in 1981. Material documents his work with the Bangor Daily News and the South-North News Service; involvement with the Maine Lobster Promotion Council; and advocacy for the JUMP playground in Ellsworth, Maine. In 1986, Dudman briefly returned on a special assignment to the St. Louis Post-Dispatch to cover the tenth anniversary of the Tangshan earthquake in China. In 1994, he returned to Vietnam on another special assignment to interview the Viet Cong officer who captured and released him and two other journalists in 1970. Both assignments are included in the papers along with other writings about and by Dudman.
1. The following description is taken from Library of Congress Acquisitions, Manuscript Division, 1979 (Washington, D.C.: 1981): 24-26. It describes the collection before the Addition series was appended to the collection in 1985.
2. Proceedings of the Massachusetts Historical Society, 1965 77 (1966): 90.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in six series:
General Correspondence, 1944-1978
Notebooks, 1970-1976
Subject File
Writings
Addition I
Addition II, 1911-2014
Container List
- General Correspondence, 1944-1978 (Box 1)
  Letters sent and received.
  Arranged chronologically by folder.
  - 1944-1949 (Box 1)
  - 1953-1978, (26 folders) (Box 1)
- Notebooks, 1970-1976 (Box 2-3)
  Reporter's notebooks.
  No arrangement.
  - 1970-1975, (44 vols.) (Box 2)
  - 1976-1978, (31 vols.) (Box 3)
- Subject File (Box 4-14)
  Correspondence, notes, reports, clippings, printed matter, and miscellaneous material compiled for background reference.
  Arranged alphabetically by topic.
  - American Conservative Union (Box 4)
  - American Enterprise Institute (Box 4)
  - American Institute of Free Labor Development (Box 4)
  - Assassinations, (3 folders) (Box 4)
  - Backlash (Box 4)
  - Birch (John) Society (Box 4)
  - Bloodbaths (Box 5)
  - Bombings (Box 5)
  - Bourne, Peter (Box 5)
  - Bundy, McGeorge (Box 5)
  - California (Box 5)
  - Central Intelligence Agency, (2 folders); (1 folder) (Box 5, Box 6)
  - Conduits (Box 6)
  - Chile (Box 6)
  - China, (3 folders) (Box 6)
  - Cuba (Box 6)
  - Dikes (Box 6)
  - Dixon-Yates contract (Box 6)
  - Dominican Republic (Box 6)
  - Drug Enforcement Agency (Box 6)
  - Ellsberg, Daniel (Box 6)
  - Fake money (Box 7)
  - Federal Bureau of Investigation (Box 7)
  - Freedom Studies Center (Box 7)
  - Freelance (Box 7)
  - Friends (Box 7)
  - Goldwater, Barry (Box 7)
  - Gould, Frank (Box 7)
  - Hanoi, Vietnam (Box 7)
  - Hanoi, Vietnam series (Box 7)
    - Dead notes (Box 7)
    - Extra copies (Box 7)
    - Memoranda (Box 8)
    - Photographs (Box 8)
  - Hiss, Alger (Box 8)
  - Humphrey, Hubert H. (Box 8)
  - Indochina, (2 folders) (Box 8)
  - Indochina, peace (Box 8)
  - Investments (Box 8)
  - Israel (Box 8)
  - Korea (Box 8)
  - Labor (Box 9)
  - Laos (Box 9)
  - Memoranda, (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - Military industrial complex (Box 10)
  - Minutemen (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous background (Box 10)
  - National Security Agency (Box 10)
  - New Directions (Box 10)
  - Nieman Fellowship (Box 10)
  - Nixon, Richard M. (Box 10)
  - Omori Research Institute (Box 10)
  - Origins (Box 10)
  - Outlines (Box 11)
  - Panama (Box 11)
  - Platforms (Box 11)
  - Postal service (Box 11)
  - Republican national convention (Box 11)
  - Revenue sharing (Box 11)
  - Sinai (Box 11)
  - South (Box 11)
  - Right wing (Box 12)
  - Rusk, Dean (Box 12)
  - Southeast Asia (Box 12)
  - Speeches, (2 folders) (Box 12)
  - Symington, Stuart (Box 12)
  - Tax privacy (Box 12)
  - Texas (Box 13)
  - Thailand-Laos (Box 13)
  - Tonkin (Box 13)
  - Travel rights (Box 13)
  - U-2 reconnaissance aircraft (Box 13)
  - Vietnam (Box 13)
    - General (Box 13)
    - Invasion (Box 13)
    - Military (Box 13)
    - Negotiations (Box 13)
    - Policy (Box 14)
    - Politics (Box 14)
    - Statistics (Box 14)
    - Visa (Box 14)
  - Warren, Earl (Box 14)
  - Watergate (Box 14)
    - General (Box 14)
    - Prosecutions (Box 14)
  - Wheat (Box 14)
  - Wyant (Box 14)
  - Zoll (Box 14)
- Writings (Box 15-23)
  Mostly clippings and printed copies of news articles but including typewritten copies and dispatches.
  Arranged by topic or type of material. Includes a scrapbook of articles.
  - Report from Hanoi, Vietnam (Box 15)
  - Vietnam 77, (11 folders) (Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 15)
  - Newspapers (Box 16-21)
  - Newspapers clippings and printed matter (Box 22)
  - Scrapbook (Box 23)
- Addition I (Box 24-67)
  Correspondence, writings, subject files, notebooks, photographs, and miscellaneous material described by topic or type of material.
  - Miscellany (Box 24)
  - Southeast Asia (Box 24)
  - Thailand (Box 24)
  - Laos (Box 24)
  - Vietnam maps (Box 24)
  - Cambodia (Box 24)
  - 1970 "Capture" materials (Box 24)
  - Newspaper and magazine articles (Box 24)
  - Cuba (Box 24)
  - Personal (Box 24)
  - Asia, 1962 (Box 24)
  - China (Box 24)
  - Vietnam (Box 25)
  - Burma (Box 25)
  - Laos (Box 25)
  - India (Box 25)
  - Southeast Asia (Box 25)
  - Thailand (Box 25)
  - Duplicates (Box 25)
  - Goldwater, Barry (Box 25)
  - Men of the Far Right, manuscript, notes, contract 26, (8 folders) (Box 26)
  - Welch, John (Box 27)
  - Prospects (Box 27)
  - Schwarz, Fred C. (Box 27)
  - Mouthpieces (Box 27)
  - Benson, George S. (Box 27)
  - Hargis, Billy James (Box 27)
  - Wyoming textbooks (Box 27)
  - Right tries (Box 27)
  - Newspaper articles (Box 27)
  - Fanaticism (Box 28)
  - Intellectuals (Box 28)
  - Action (Box 28)
  - China picture information, 1972 (Box 28)
  - Taiwan, 1972 (Box 28)
  - Tokyo, Japan, 1972 (Box 28)
  - Vietnam, 1972 (Box 29)
  - Duplicates, 1972 (Box 29)
  - Personal, 1972 (Box 29)
  - Printed matter (Box 29)
  - Other, 1972 (Box 29)
  - Hanoi, Vietnam (Box 29)
  - Laos photographs, 1959 (Box 29)
  - Symington, Stuart (Box 29)
  - Materials relating to 1970 capture (Box 30)
  - South Vietnam (Box 30)
  - Printed matter (Box 30)
  - China dispatches, 1972 (Box 30)
  - China (Box 30)
  - Office files (Box 30)
  - Hate mail (Box 30)
  - Miscellany (Box 30)
  - Dudman, Helen, 1970-1975, (5 folders) (Box 31)
  - Dudman, Richard, 1970-1974 (Box 31)
  - Forty Days with the Enemy (Box 32)
    - Notes, reviews, rough drafts, proofs (Box 32)
    - Notes, reviews, rough drafts, proofs (Box 33)
  - China with Gerald Ford, 1976 (Box 33)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 34-38)
  - Printed matter (Box 34-38)
  - China and Hanoi, Vietnam, Dudman photographs, 1970-1972 (Box 39)
  - Notebooks, diaries, press passes, 1958-1977 (Box 40)
  - Scrapbooks, 1946-1965 (Box 41-47)
  - Scrapbooks and poster (Box 48)
  - Notebooks, 1954-1981 (Box 49-50)
  - Angola (Box 51)
  - Alaska (Box 51)
  - Arab boycott (Box 51)
  - Arms control (Box 51)
  - Asbestos (Box 51)
  - B'nai B'rith (Box 51)
  - Brookings Institution, Washington, D.C. (Box 51)
  - Cambodia, (2 folders); (4 folders) (Box 51, Box 52)
  - Caric (Box 52)
  - Carter, Jimmy, administration (Box 52)
    - General (Box 52)
    - Campaign (Box 53)
    - Foreign policy (Box 53)
    - Promises (Box 53)
  - Central Intelligence Agency, (3 folders) (Box 53)
  - China (Box 53)
  - Clemency (Box 54)
  - Connally, John B. (Box 54)
  - Correspondence, (4 folders) (Box 54)
  - Columns (Box 54)
  - Detainees (Box 54)
  - Dispute (Box 54)
  - Dogs (Box 54)
  - Egypt (Box 55)
  - Election financing (Box 55)
  - Executive privilege (Box 55)
  - Food for Peace (Box 55)
  - Freedom of information (Box 55)
  - Freedom Studies Center (Box 56)
  - Freelance (Box 56)
  - Future, (2 folders) (Box 56)
  - Glomar Explorer suppression (Box 56)
  - Gridiron (Box 56)
  - Halperin, Morton (Box 57)
  - Hanoi, Vietnam, (2 folders) (Box 57)
  - Helsinki Accords (Box 57)
  - Indonesia (Box 57)
  - Institute for Policy Studies (Box 57)
  - Intelligence (Box 58)
  - ITT Corp., (2 folders) (Box 58)
  - Jewish vote (Box 58)
  - Job applications (Box 58)
  - Justice (Box 59)
  - Kennedy, Edward (Box 59)
  - Kissinger, Henry (Box 59)
  - LaRoque, Gene (Box 59)
  - Latin America (Box 59)
  - Memoranda (Box 59)
  - Nieman Foundation (Box 59)
  - Nixon Doctrine (Box 59)
  - North Atlantic Treaty Organization (Box 59)
  - Oil (Box 59)
  - Phone, (1 folder) (Box 59, Box 60)
  - Post-Dispatch future (Box 60)
  - Pending assignments (Box 60)
  - Presidency (Box 60)
  - Press (Box 60)
  - Privacy (Box 60)
  - Pulitzer (Box 60)
  - Rhodesia (Box 60)
  - Right wing (Box 60)
  - Rusk, Dean (Box 61)
  - St. Louis Post-Dispatch v. F.B.I., (2 folders) (Box 61)
  - SALT I and SALT II (Strategic Arms Limitations Talks), (2 folders) (Box 62)
  - Securities and Exchange Commission (Box 62)
  - Schorr, Daniel (Box 62)
  - Staff meetings (Box 62)
  - Synfuel (Box 62)
  - Systems (Box 62)
  - Taiwan, (2 folders) (Box 62)
  - Terror (Box 62)
  - TRB (newspaper column). (Box 62)
  - Vietnam, (4 folders) (Box 63)
  - Washington Journalism Center, Washington, D.C. (Box 63)
  - Wilson, Woodrow, (2 folders) (Box 63)
  - Writings (Box 64)
  - Printed matter (Box 64)
  - Printed matter (Box 65)
  - Newspapers and newspaper clippings (Box 66-67)
- Addition II, 1911-2014 (Box 68-70)
  Writings, correspondence, photographs, printed matter, subject files, and other papers.
  Arranged alphabetically by topic or type of material.
  - Awards, 1979-1981, 1994 (Box 68)
  - Biographies and résumés, 1990-1997, 2004, 2013 (Box 68)
  - General correspondence, 1970-2001, 2007, 2013, undated, (2 folders) (Box 68)
  - JUMP playground, 1985-1986, 1999 (Box 68)
  - Miscellany, 1970, 1979, 1987-1994, 2007, undated (Box 68)
  - National Pork Producers Council v. Maine Lobster Promotion Council, 1993-1998 (Box 68)
  - Newseum, 1952, 1968-1969, 1990, 1997-1998, 2006-2007, undated (Box 68)
  - Photographs, 1924, 1959, 1972-1980, 1989, undated (Box 68)
  - Pulitzer family, 1911, 1929, 1947-1954, 1960-1965, 1972, 1978 (Box 68)
  - South Africa, 1988-1996 (Box 68)
  - St. Louis Post-Dispatch, 1947, 1972, 1979-1981, 1990-2005, undated (Box 69)
  - Stone, I. F., 1968, 2006 (Box 69)
  - Tangshan earthquake, 1986 (Box 69)
  - Vietnam, 1969-1982, 1988-1994, 2007, (3 folders) (Box 69)
  - World Wise, 1992-1995 (Box 69)
  - Writings (Box 69)
    - About Dudman, 1971, 1980-1998, 2013-2014, undated, (2 folders); (1 folder) (Box 70)
    - By Dudman, 1956, 1963-1964, 1970-2013, undated, (5 folders)